Got to love those inflammatory words,
toxic, like Britney Spears hit song. But
those aren't my words or even Britney's.
They're actually the words of the
researchers. It turns out that as your
kidney function worsens, a previously
rare toxic protein begins to present
itself in your arteries, leading to some
pretty devastating consequences. The
protein is proje and it's actually a
cautionary tale for why keeping your
kidney health an overlooked organ
although nefologists would beg to differ
intact is critical to avoiding blood
vessel damage. The reality is pieran has
been known about for some time but it's
mainly been attributed to people with
Hutchinson Guilford piera syndrome which
is a rare genetic disorder but now we're
learning that it is far more relevant to
people like you and me people with
otherwise genetically healthy kidneys as
projerine can build up and cause havoc
in our arteries. Typically, your kidneys
are like a filtration plant, like for
your water in your town, but they filter
your blood and remove, I'm going to say
it again, toxic molecules called uremic
toxins. These uh come in many shapes and
sizes that we don't need to get into.
Just know that your kidneys remove
uremic toxins from your blood and
dispose of it in your urine.
Unfortunately, as your kidney health
declines, which we'll get into some ways
of easily checking that later, there's a
rise in the protein progenine. PGRine
arises due to the damage of these uremic
toxins cause on the genes within our
cells. In this case, cells of the
arteries that ultimately causes a
mutation leading to the production of
progen. So in this study the researchers
discovered in people as seen here that
people with bad kidneys so CKD there
have greater perjurine levels compared
to people with healthy kidneys the
remaining condition. If the dots go up
that means that there's more perjury
these people do not have this inherent
Hutchinson Guilford syndrome. These are
people like I said before like you and
me that have poor kidney health
independent of their genetics. Okay. But
how exactly does this toxic progerine
gunk up or build up in our arteries?
Well, you know how you have to have
blood pressure or you die? If you've
never thought about it before, now you
can. Your blood is in a closed system, a
system of dynamic, biologically active
pipes. If you zoom into those pipes,
there's a multiple types of cells and
non-ell architecture that control your
blood pressure by squeezing or relaxing
the blood vessels. So in short these
arterial cells control your blood
pressure. Now since we know that
progerine is spontaneously produced due
to this mutation caused by the toxins
not flushed out by the damaged kidneys.
What are the consequences of proggerine
in these arterial cells? Well
surprisingly the researchers did a cell
proliferation assay. Essentially they
wanted to test the growth and division
of arterial cells. Now what would you
expect to happen? cells exposed to this
toxic protein are going to grow more or
less. If you said less, you are, I think
counterintuitively, wrong. The
researchers actually indicated that
these cells have more growth markers.
So, the arterial cells burdened with
progen tend to multiply. And if you
think about it, that may be worse
considering that you're essentially
growing unhealthy cells faster than
you're growing healthy arterial cells.
So imagine that happens over time as
there's more dysfunctional cells than
functional cells in your arteries. Now
look, maybe when you were a kid, you
were so frustrated with life or your
parents that you declared that you were
running away from home. Well, projed
arterial cells don't just threaten it,
they do it. The researchers examined
slices of arteries here. And the red
outline is the border of the artery and
the white specks are the specific artery
cells that we're concerned with called
smooth muscle cells, the ones that
directly control blood pressure. The top
image is the normal artery. So you can
see that the cells remain inside the red
border. And the bottom image is the
cells with proger toxicity.
They said just screw you dad. I'm
leaving a mass exodus from their
designated position. So, think about
that for a moment. If your arterial
cells leave their post, what does that
do for the integrity of your arteries?
Nothing good. I can tell you that much.
In fact, what replaces them might be
worse. Because if we look at another
image of what the arteries look like,
all I need you to notice is the lighter
coloring on the right image as well as
the lack of organized structure compared
to the left image, which is an image of
healthy artery. That discoloration and
the lack of structure is due to what
happens when space needs to be filled
where arterial cells used to be located,
but they've left their post. Remember
that space is filled with fibrous
tissue. Essentially, collagen gets
deposited to maintain the structure as
well as possible. Now, remember when I
asked you if you thought uh there might
be fewer of the arterial cells if proger
accumulates? Well, I guess you were kind
of right. And in fact, I'll go ahead and
tell you that the smooth muscle cells,
the arterial cells also have been dying
from the stress. I don't mean that like
an exam coming up and you're like I'm
dying but actually dying from the progen
accumulation. It really is almost like
an infection. So we now see this chain
of events. Poor kidney health leads to
an accumulation of this uremic toxins in
the blood that particularly physically
damage the genes of the arterial cells
with one in particular that causes a
sudden unwanted production of a toxic
protein projection
dividing more leaving their posts in the
artery wall and dying. That's the sum of
it. But where there are problems, there
are also solutions. Hey, there are
solutions, right?
Did we not did we not know Sol? They're
going to have my head. Okay, I've been
informed uh by my producer that we do in
fact have solutions. Hey, and if you're
ever dissatisfied with the level of
detail here, I actually go over much
more on how progenine affects your body.
Some of the other strange things that
your artery cells do, an age effect, and
even a potent molecule that may help
clear progen from the cells coming from
another study. That's all in my full
analysis, which is included for the
physiotic insiders. Plus, all these
perks. If you're looking for a deeper
dive, that's the place to be. We can
even discuss it in one of my live
sessions that I regularly do if you are
so inclined. Anyway, up to you. Link to
join the insiders in the description.
So, the solutions center around the
beginning of this cascade, the kidney.
As we saw, people with healthy kidneys
do not have this association to increase
perjurine. And I will say as we age,
progine levels may rise. Anyway, the
point being the first step is to test
your kidney health, which you can
rudimentarily do using your usual blood
test. So using metrics like serum,
creatinine, uh, eGFR, and blood ura
nitrogen, any one of those or a
combination of those. However, I should
point out that if you supplement with
creatine or you work out a lot, some of
these measures can report back
artificially poor results. So in that
case getting a cystatin C test can be a
better marker although you may have to
pay extra or ask for it. Then there are
some more burdensome tests like
urinalysis and others but those I
mentioned before are a great start. So
then how do we maintain healthy kidneys?
Well there's plenty of things that you
can do actually. I'll list a few here.
For one high blood sugar can create
detrimental molecules called aes which
impair kidney function. So focusing on
reducing blood sugar can make a
significant difference. So low carb
diets, Mediterranean diets are just a
few ways to do that. That in addition to
exercise surprisingly also directly
benefits the kidney function along with
reducing blood sugar levels. A second
thing is to avoid nephrotoxins. These
are molecules that you're exposed to
that directly harm your kidneys. So one
perfect example is the overconumption of
certain drugs like non-steroidal
anti-inflammatory drugs. In the short
term, it's likely not a big issue, but
being dependent on them can definitely
be detrimental. A third thing is to
reduce your blood pressure as high blood
pressure can harm your kidneys. Not to
mention the harm to your arteries that
are already struggling. Again, nutrition
and exercise have potent effects on your
blood pressure. In fact, particular
exercises have a tremendous effect, and
I'll speak on that more in a minute. So
everything considered, keeping your
kidneys healthy keeps your arterial
cells from being exposed to undue DNA
damage resulting in the production of
the toxic protein projection
and death in the artery. We can avoid
that from ever happening by one testing
our kidney function and two focusing on
prevention and re reversal of kidney
harm like keeping your blood sugar
normal, avoiding nephrotoxins like over
consuming pain relief drugs. And a big
one is reducing your blood pressure. And
it's on that last one that we can
actually perform a simple one minute
exercise that has tremendous longlasting
blood pressure lowering effects. I
detail more on the science of how to do
it right here. Thanks for tuning in.